Inventory of the Xie Chi papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Xie Chi papers
1913-1929
2007C47
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Relates to China.
Xie, Chi, 1876-1939
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers include diaries, correspondence, telegrams, and photographs related to political leaders of China in the early part of the twentieth century.
Biographical/Historical note
Chinese politician.
Biographical Note
1876 Born, in Sichuan Province, China
1900 Entered the Jingwei Academy at Yibin, Sichuan Studied under Zhou Shaohuai
1902 Graduated from the Jingwei Academy Followed Zhou to Chengdu
1903 Appointed as a physical education instructor in a police academy Became a superintendent of school construction for the Sichuan office of education
1907 Appointed as the superintendent of trade by the Sichuan government Plotted a revolutionary takeover of the city on Oct. 2 but the plan failed
1909 Joined Tongmenghui in Chongqing Returned to Shanghai to serve as provost at new Shu Shuang Gong Suo Sent to Fengxiang, Shanxi to work as shepherds and engaged in anti-Manchu activities
1911 Plotted to take over Chongqing Chongqing declared its independence on Nov. 22 Elected director of the general affairs bureau of the new military government in Chongqing
1912 Appointed as the vice director of the general affairs of the military government of Sichuan
1913 Elected to the Senate Plotted to assassinate Yuan Shikai but the plot was discovered by Yuan’s agents Arrested on May 17 but escaped indictment Fled to Japan to assist Sun Yat-sen in organizing Kuomintang
1918-1919 Served Sun Yat-sen in the Canton government as vice minister of justice Elected to the director of the department of party affairs
1919-1921 Served as vice minister of interior
1921-1922 Served as secretary general of the presidential office
1924 Elected one of the five members of the Central Supervisory Committee by the First National Congress of the recognized Kuomintang
1926 Expelled by the leftist faction of the Kuomintang and joined the Western Hills faction
1927-1929 Named to the special committee by the Western Hills faction Withdrawn from the government and retired to Shanghai
1930 Elected to the standing committee of the enlarged conference which serves as the decision-making organ of the Kuomintang in opposition to the party apparatus functioning in Nanjing Left for Tianjin to seek safety after the conference was dissolved
1931 Listed by the Canton leaders as a member of their government council Went to Shanghai after the peace meeting between the Nanjing and Canton leaders had been successfully concluded
1937 Returned to his native Sichuan from Shanghai
1939 Died on April 16
China--History.
- Diaries (6 volumes) 日记 （六卷）, 17 May 1913 - 31 Dec 1918 (Box 1)
- Diaries (5 volumes) 日记 （五卷）, 31 Jan 1924 - 24 Dec 1928 (Box 1)
- Telegrams, memos and documents 电报，函件，文件等, 1913 - 1923 (Box 2)
  - Records relating to Xie Chi arrest's for assasination plot against Yuan Shikai, Senate interrogatories, Congress response 谢持被捕，参议院质问书，国务院复函, May 1913 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Chen Yucun 致陈雨村电, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Yang Cangbai 致杨沧白电, 21 Mar 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Lu Xiqing 致卢锡卿电, 24 Mar 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram from Wanxian Bureau 万县局来电, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Liu Gongqian 致刘公潜, 7 May 1923 (Box 2)
  - Petition on Yandian from Senators and Congressmen in Guangdong and Sichuan 驻粤四川参议两院议员有关艳电之呈文, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Council meeting notes/memos 各总裁各代表政务会议议事日程, Mar 10 (Box 2)
  - Military Plans 军事计划, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Central Committee secret meeting motion 中央党部秘密决议案, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Mar 12 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Apr 8 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Apr 10 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Apr 10 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Apr 13 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, Apr 24 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, May 3 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, May 5 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, May 5 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Sun Yat-sen 致孙中山电, May 7 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Yang Cangbai, Lu Xiqing, and others 致杨沧白、卢锡卿诸人电, May 5 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Yang Cangbai, Lu Xiqing, and Sun Yat-sen 致杨沧白、卢锡卿并呈孙中山电, Mar 31 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Yang Cangbai, Lu Xiqing, and Sun Yat-sen 致杨沧白、卢锡卿并呈孙中山电, Apr 17 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Yang Cangbai, Lu Xiqing, and Sun Yat-sen 致杨沧白、卢锡卿并呈孙中山电, Apr 4 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Lu Xiqing 致卢锡卿电, Apr 23 1923 (Box 2)
  - 2 telegrams 电文两件, Mar 14 1923 (Box 2)
  - 1 letter reply 复函一件, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Yang Chunfang 致杨春芳函, Apr 10 1923 (Box 2)
  - 59th Council meeting agenda 第五十九次政务会议议事日程, Mar 17 (Box 2)
  - Suggestion to invite Sun Yat-sen to assume provisional presidency 有关请孙中山任临时大总统的建议, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Sichuan provisional government’s memo to protest election law 四川临时省政府执行委员会就选举法提出抗议书, Jul 13 1925 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Chengdu Warlord Xiong 致成都熊督军函, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Telegram to Lu Xiqing 致卢锡卿电, Mar 12 1923 (Box 2)
  - Declaration of Kuomindang 1st National Congress 中国国民党第一次全国代表大会宣言, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Order to conduct Chinese-Soviet relations 与中俄交涉事令, 1924 (Box 2)
- 2 photographies of Xie Chi 谢持个人照两张, undated (Box 2)
- 2 photographs of Xie Chi and Zou Lu taken in Beijing 谢持与邹鲁合照两张, 1925 (Box 2)
- Group photo of Xie Chi and others 谢持和其他人士团体照, undated (Box 2)
- 2 photo negatives of Xie Chi and others 谢持和其他人团体照底片两张, undated (Box 2)
- Copies of Xie Chi’s address book, 46 pages 谢持人名地址簿46张, undated (Box 2)
- Poem compilation of Fan Wenyu (Daughter in law of Xie Chi) 范问余（谢持之儿媳）诗集, undated (Box 2)
- Memoir of Zhu Zhihong's and Zhu Biqian's participation in the Xin Hai Revolution authored by Peng Yongyi 朱必洪朱必谦先生参加辛亥革命前后的事略, May 4 1981 (Box 2)
- “Kuomindang historical manuscript” authored Zou Lu, originally published by the Shanghai Minzhi Bookstore, 1929. Pages 379-406, 411-421 邹鲁著“中国国名党史稿”原稿 -上海民智书局民国十八年版 379-406；411-421页 (Box 2)
- Summary of the development of Chinese Communist Party and current labor movement 综述中国共产党发展经过及目前劳工运动, 1918 - 1923 (Box 2)
- Summary of Kuomindang 国名党民国三年至十三年简述, 1914-1924 (Box 2)
- Summary of activities in SiChuan 川省进行概要, 1926 (Box 2)